A Guide to the Papers of the Virginia Quarterly Review, 1928, 1940,1996-2006
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Virginia Quarterly Review
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
RG-24/3/1.071
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Box 6 is restricted.
Acquisitions
The collection was an archival transfer from the Virginia Quarterly Review to Special Collections on June 21, 2007
Biographical/Historical Information
The Virginia Quarterly Review was established in 1925 and was originally conceived by President Edwin Alderman in 1915. President Alderman wanted the University of Virginia to publish a national periodical that "was solidly based, thoughtfully and wisely managed and controlled ... a great serious publication wherein it shall be focused and set down the very best thought ... of men everywhere in the nation and the world on vital questions in the fields of Economics, Politics, Ethics, Literary Interpretation and Historical Analysis ...."
The first editor was James Southall Wilson, followed by Stringfellow Barr, Lambert Davis (who was able to maintain the journal through the Depression) Lawrence Lee, Archibald Shepperson, and Charlotte Kohler. The VQR was in the hands of its first woman editor during World War II when the men were away at war. Kohler's tenure lasted for an impressive thirty three years. In 1975 Staige Blackford became the editor and continued the high standards set by President Alderman until his retirement and death in 2003. The next editor was Theodore "Ted" Genoways who with support from key staff has continued to uphold the Virginia Quarterly Review as "a national journal of literature and discussion." (Quotes are taken from Staige Blackford's foreword in the Anthology of the 75th Anniversary publication, "We Write for Our Own Time")
Scope and Content
The collection consists chiefly of editorial correspondence files and miscellaneous office files of Staige D. Blackford and Ted Genoways as editors of The Virginia Quarterly Review covering the years 1928; 1940; 1996-2006. There is also some correspondence from former editor Charlotte Kohler (editor 1946-1975) from the years 1958-1971. Included are files on copyright permissions and renewals, financial information, publicity, newspaper advertising (1940- 2006), contracts and correspondence with contributors, mailing lists, photographs, press releases, subscriptions and memorabilia. The collection is about 3,000 items, 6 hollinger boxes, and 2.5 linear feet.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by topic and the editorial correspondence with authors is alphabetical by last name.
Contents List
- 1996-1998 Anthology "We Write for Our Own Time", # items (Box-folder 1:1)
  Alex Burnham worked with Staige Davis Blackford, Jr. and the Virginia Press to publish an anthology of essays from the Virginia Quarterly Review for the 75 th anniversary of the journal. It was originally titled, "A Jefferson Harvesting" but the Virginia Press changed the name to "We Write for Our Own Time" There is an Introduction, book proposal, table of contents and correspondence about the book
- 1999 Anthology "We Write for Our Own Time", # items (Box-folder 1:2)
  There is correspondence between Staige Blackford, Alex Burnham and the University Press about the book
- 1989-1992 Articles Eric Clapton's Lover, # items (Box-folder 1:3)
- 1999 Articles Faulkner's Unpublished Story, # items (Box-folder 1:4)
- 2003-2006 Correspondence Ted Genoways with Authors Abramson-Czyzynjewski, # items (Box-folder 1:5)
  Correspondence with Ted Genoways and the authors regarding acceptance and rejection of their work for the Virginia Quarterly Review
- 2003-2006 Correspondence Ted Genoways and Authors Davidson-Furtney, # items (Box-folder 1:6)
- 2003-2006 Correspondence Ted Genoways and Authors Galvin-Grotz, # items (Box-folder 2:1)
- 2003-2006 Correspondence Ted Genoways and Authors Haggard-Kuznets, # items (Box-folder 2:2)
- 2003-2006 Correspondence Ted Genoways and Authors LaSalle-Lynch, # items (Box-folder 2:3)
- 2003-2006 Correspondence Ted Genoways and Authors McBride-Owen, # items (Box-folder 2:4)
- 2003-2006 Correspondence Ted Genoways and Authors Pacheco- Rubenstein, # items (Box-folder 2:5)
- 2003-2006 Correspondence Ted Genoways with Authors Saunders-Sward, # items (Box-folder 2:6)
- 2003-2006 Correspondence Ted Genoways with Authors Taylor-Zwiep, # items (Box-folder 3:1)
- 1994-2003 Authors, # items (Box-folder 3:2)
  There is a list of authors that contributed to the Virginia Quarterly Review
- 2004Spring Author Contracts, # items (Box-folder 3:3)
  There are signed contracts for authors who had work accepted by the Virginia Quarterly Review
- 2004Summer Author Contracts, # items (Box-folder 3:4)
- 2004Fall Author Contracts, # items (Box-folder 3:5)
- 2004Winter Author Contracts, # items (Box-folder 3:6)
- 2005Spring Author Contracts, # items (Box-folder 3:7)
- 2005Summer Author Contracts, # items (Box-folder 3:8)
- 2005Fall Contracts, # items (Box-folder 3:9)
- 2005Winter Author Contracts, # items (Box-folder 4:1)
- 1998-2000 Copyright Permissions, # items (Box-folder 4:2)
- n. d. Awards, # items (Box-folder 4:3)
  Miscellaneous information about fiction, short story, and poetry awards
- 2002-2003 Copyright Permission, # items (Box-folder 4:4)
- 2004-2006 Copyright Permission, # items (Box-folder 4:5)
- 1960-1998 Copyright Renewals, # items (Box-folder 4:6)
- 1976-2003 Correspondence Staige Davis Blackford, Jr., # items (Box-folder 4:7)
- 1958-1971 Correspondence Charlotte Kohler, # items (Box-folder 4:8)
- 1997-2004 Financial Records, # items (Box-folder 4:9)
  There are miscellaneous invoices; working orders; and printing costs for (Alex Burnham's) anthology, "We Write for Our Own Time." There is a letter from Kenneth E. Sinarski (auditor) to Ted Genoways mentioning the $830,000 surplus left by Staige D. Blackford and describing the financial condition of the VQR since Genoways took it over in July 2003 as well as balance sheets for 2003 and endowment fund summaries for 2004.
- 1989-2004 Financial Records and relationship with the University of Virginia, # items (Box-folder 4:10)
  There is correspondence of Staige Blackford about endowment and investment funds (Balch, Weedon) and the question of whether or not the VQR had the authority to invest funds independently or invest through the University (the latter is what they did). Other correspondents include Kenneth E. Sinarski, and Leonard Sandridge. Also included are historical documents concerning the relationship between the VQR and the University (1955-1969) with correspondents such as Vincent Shea, Charlotte Kohler, C. F. Cassell, R. Sturgis Ingersoll, and Archibald B. Shepperson. There are also balance sheets from 1999 through 2002.
- 1974 Honor System, # items (Box-folder 4:11)
  There is a list of honor advisors and memos to the faculty about the rules of the honor code.
- 1998 Licenses and Royalties, # items (Box-folder 4:12)
  There are license agreements and royalties for the Virginia Quarterly Review from UMI and Gale Group
- 1944-1988 Marketing, # items (Box-folder 4:13)
  There is correspondence about placement of advertisements in various schools, newspapers, magazines, and subscription agencies
- 1983-1996 Marketing, # items (Box-folder 5:1)
  There is information about marketing strategies, and subscription lists for the Virginia Quarterly Review
- 1940-1973 Marketing, # items (Box-folder 5:2)
  There are subscription cards for these years encouraging people to give the Virginia Quarterly Review as a gift
- 1986-2003 Newspaper clippings about Staige Davis Blackford, Jr., # items (Box-folder 5:3)
  Included is a resolution passed by the General Assembly of the Commonwealth of Virginia noting the sadness of the death of Staige D. Blackford and recognizing his achievements
- 1958-1959; 1976-2003 Newspaper clippings about the Virginia Quarterly Review, # items (Box-folder 5:4)
- n. d. Newspaper clippings, # items (Box-folder 5:5)
  Newspaper clippings about various topics but mostly regarding significant authors and literature
- 2000 Planning for the Anniversary of the Virginia Quarterly Review, # items (Box-folder 5:6)
  There is correspondence about the 75 th anniversary of the VQR including a party at the Rotunda, a guest list and a program
- n.d.; 2000 Photographs, # items (Box-folder 5:7)
  There are photographs from the 75 th anniversary of the VQR party at the Rotunda; a photograph of a portrait of James Southall Wilson (the 1 st editor of the VQR in 1925;) and photographs of a presentation given to the VQR and Staige Blackford at the 70 th year anniversary at Barnes and Noble
- n. d. Proofs for the Virginia Quarterly Review, # items (Box-folder 5:8)
- 1975; 1993 Table of Contents of the Virginia Quarterly Review, # items (Box-folder 5:9)
  There are photocopies of the table of contents for several issues
- 1976-1989 Virginia Press Releases, # items (Box-folder 5:10)
  There are miscellaneous press releases about the Supreme Court, President Jimmy Carter, articles in the VQR and articles written by the University of Virginia Faculty
- 1928-2004 Virginia Quarterly Review Office Restorations, # items (Box-folder 5:11)
  There is correspondence, photographs, and architectural designs regarding alterations to the office of the VQR, One West Range
- Restricted due to social security numbers and identification numbers
  - 1969-1973; 1977-1979; 1981-1989 Income Tax Forms, # items (Box-folder 6:1)
    Income tax forms for the VQR
  - 1998 Copyright Agreements, # items (Box-folder 6:2)
  - 1994 Financial Tax Forms for Authors, # items (Box-folder 6:3)
  - 1995 Financial Tax Forms for Authors, # items (Box-folder 6:4)
  - 1995-1996 Financial Tax Forms for Authors, # items (Box-folder 6:5)
  - 1997 Financial Tax Forms for Authors, # items (Box-folder 6:6)
  - 1998 Financial Tax Forms for Authors, # items (Box-folder 6:7)
  - 1998-1999 Financial Tax Forms for Authors, # items (Box-folder 6:8)
  - 2000 Financial Tax Forms for Authors, # items (Box-folder 6:9)
  - 2001 Financial Tax Forms for Authors, # items (Box-folder 6:10)
  - 2002 Financial Tax Forms for Authors, # items (Box-folder 6:11)
  - 2003 Financial Tax Forms for Authors, # items (Box-folder 6:12)